Hi, welcome back to Gift of Liberation.
And this is Geshe Michael.
I'm excited about our course.
It's going to be a very deep course
and we're going to continue
talking about this idea,
everybody talks about bodhichitta,
and we hear this word of bodhichitta.
And I think a few people still think
it means enlightenment mind,
and then they think it
means the mind of a Buddha
because bodhi means Buddha
and chitta means mind.
Of course it doesn't mean that.
What it means is the Wish
to reach enlightenment.
If we study it for two or three courses,
Lam Rim courses, two or three retreats,
then I think we also start to
forget what is bodhichitta.
You can say as the Wish for
enlightenment. That's okay.
But I very much prefer if you
have the real feeling of it
and the feeling is completely different.
It's not to sit and like when you're a kid
and you're wishing for
a bicycle for Christmas.
It's not like that.
It's not like that. It's
a different kind of thing.
So I thought maybe at
the very beginning here
we can do a small meditation,
just a few minutes.
You can do a longer one
in your extra classes.
But let's just do a short meditation
on what this bodhichitta feel like.
And that way we can do the whole course
and we can remember
where we're trying to go.
I will describe the experience
of bodhichitta directly
and then you just follow
along and imagine it.
And I don't know,
when I was in sports when I
played tennis in high school,
they would tell us to imagine yourself
making these great plays and
doing these great things.
My yoga teacher told me
if you can't do a pose,
then just go halfway into a headstand
and then imagine yourself
in the headstand.
Then that's a cause for
being able to do it.
So we're going to do the
same thing with bodhichitta.
So please get ready.
We're going to do just the
little tiny meditation.
You do your serious meditations
in your extra classes.
Eyes are soft. A little bit of a smile.
Hands are soft. Fingers are soft.
I like to touch my thumbs.
I like to put my palms on each other.
Sit up very straight. Shoulders back.
I like to...
A strange thing about
pulling in your tummy is
if you exhale two times,
your stomach will come in automatically.
That's just good for your posture
and it's good for your health.
So let's do long exhales.
When you run out of breath,
push a little bit more breath out
and your lower stomach will tighten
and that will support your back.
Okay, here we go. 10 long exhales.
And we'll imagine that we're
having the direct experience
of bodhichitta and imagine
your mom comes up in your mind.
It's not a picture. It's not a painting.
It's not a photograph.
It's your real mom, is
in front of your mind.
And it's nice to picture her in her health
when you knew her or you saw photos of her
when she was young and healthy, happy.
And you're just sitting together.
And you're like talking to her,
"Look, Mom, I know your
life has not been easy.
Life is not always easy.
I know you have worries.
Wherever you are now, I
know you have more worries.
I know you have trouble in your life.
And we have that big fear of death
but I want you to know that
I'm going to take care of you.
It's not an empty
promise. I have the power.
I am learning the power
to take care of you.
You really don't have to worry.
So kids are supposed to
take care of their parents
when they get older,
and I've got plans for taking care of you.
I will be a Buddha, a real
Buddha who can go to all places,
all times, all worlds,
and knows all things
and can help you, real help for you.
I'm on a fast track for that.
So you don't have to worry.
I know it's my job to take care of you
the way you took care of me
and you don't have to worry.
I'm on a path and it works.
I can see where it's going and I can see
that I will take care of you ultimately."
And try to picture that day
when you have power to
move from world to world,
planet to planet, galaxy to
galaxy, in countless bodies.
It feels like dancing across worlds
and taking care of everyone in each world.
Imagine that power.
Your mind has that power
because your mind is empty.
You have that power. You
just have to wake it up.
Creating a mandala, perfect world,
perfect universe where no one suffers,
no one gets old, no one dies.
You have that power. You
are learning how to do it.
You are a Buddha in training.
But don't ever forget where you're going
and why we are doing these courses.
Make that promise to your mom.
Okay, then you can open your eyes.
Take a stretch me and mom.
(laughs)
So this course in the Lam Rim,
and we've been going
for almost 10 years now,
over 10 years, and we're
working our way very,
I don't know, for me it's a
great pleasure to come back
to the Lam Rim every few
months in the last 10 years.
For me, it's like swimming in a sauna.
I don't know how you call
this heated swimming pool,
or the ocean at San Pacho, or
San Miguel, on very nice day.
It just feels so pleasant
to come back to the beach
called Lam Rim and jump in the water again
and kind of get my motivation back,
and get my courage back again,
and then my life doesn't
seem so difficult,
and I can dream again
about becoming a Buddha.
This book, oh, it's got to be
the greatest book ever written
for the entire Buddhist path.
If you can read Tibetan,
every single word is extremely beautiful.
It makes you think that
Trijang Rinpoche was a special,
very special being, my teacher's teacher.
So you're of a good lineage.
And we're going to continue.
I'm going to review what
we did in the last Lam Rim,
which was what's the cool stuff
that's going to happen to you
if you can get bodhichitta,
if you can really reach this motivation
and this vision.
Never forget the vision.
I don't even like to call it motivation.
Get that vision in your mind of traveling
from planet to planet and
jumping between planets.
It's a lot of fun and you can do it.
Don't think this is the only planet.
Come on. Go out and look
at the stars some night.
So keep that in mind.
We're going to review
the last Lam Rim we had.
The subject of the last Lam
Rim was really focusing on ten,
It's called PHAN YON BCU,
which is the ten benefits of bodhichitta,
the Wish for enlightenment.
If you can reach it,
if you can have that direct experience,
then what's it going to feel like
and how you're going to feel?
So we're going to go
through those ten benefits.
I'm going to show some IDIMS,
some pictures that give
you a idea of the benefit.
The first one we can show,
so when we talk about the first benefit
of reaching this kind of vision
of jumping between planets,
dancing between planets,
there are ten benefits.
This is a picture of the first benefit.
I like to call it Visiting
the Middle of the Sun.
And this is called
THEG CHEN GYI 'JUG SGO SEMS
BSKYED KHO NAR BSTAN PA
It means you will enter the greater way,
and it's like going to
the middle of the sun.
Why do I say middle of the sun?
Because it's a very intense, good karma,
a very, very high good karma.
The good karma of
imagining yourself dancing
between planets and helping
people is incredible.
Just the good karma of imagining it is...
You can even feel it, right?
When I first taught this last summer,
we were talking about the virus
and how could we help to stop the virus?
We were talking about,
if we could send the virus
to the middle of the sun,
then that would be great.
Then it'd be great if
we could send the virus
to be destroyed in the middle of the sun.
And also in between that time,
we had the Medicine Buddha
retreat and all of us were
doing a lot of dedication,
helping save the life of animals,
thinking of ways to save the environment
with our carbon offset program,
and different ways of
helping life on this planet,
for example, not eating meat.
Then people started to write me,
"Oh, things are happening.
This karma is working."
I think, I don't know about you guys,
but in America we are very,
what do you call that?
We don't believe those things.
We were very skeptical.
We're like, "Ah, come on,
don't be superstitious."
Yeah, we studied the Medicine Buddha.
Yeah, we meditated on saving life.
Yeah, we made plans to stop pollution
and save the forest. But come on,
it's not really going to
change things like that.
But suddenly, I don't know about you,
but I started noticing things happening.
The vaccination came out.
The vaccination was finished.
They used to take 10 years,
20 years, to develop a vaccination.
And this one was developed
in less than a year.
And then they started giving it
and I actually didn't call anybody.
I didn't plan to get a vaccination.
Just some friends called
me, "Oh, go there.
They're going to give you a vaccination."
I went there and I got my vaccination.
Veronica got a vaccination.
Jigme got a vaccination,
first and second one.
Now suddenly, yesterday
we went to a restaurant
for the first time and
we had such a good time
not wearing masks.
It was so pleasant.
Yhen suddenly things started happening.
McDonald's announced...
I was looking for a recipe
to cook something at home
because Veronica is a very good cook
and Geshe Michael is an okay
cook but not like Veronica.
And I thought, "Oh, I want
to learn some new recipes."
I was looking for vegetarian food
and I found an advertisement
from McDonald's.
They are making a vegetarian
meat, plant-based meat.
And it's a big, big thing now
in Asia, in Singapore, for example.
You can get your Chicken
McNuggets are made from plants.
This guy was so cute.
He said, "Okay, I'm going to cook some.
I bought some uncooked
and we're going to cook them together."
I was watching the cook's video
and he cooked this non-meat chicken,
and then he showed how to cook it,
and then he tried it.
Then he tried one and when he was like,
"Oh my God, that tastes so good."
And I was like, "Yay!"
McDonald's announced they're going to
serve it in McDonald's.
And I was so happy.
Then Bill Gates, one of the
wealthiest guys in the world,
he finished a book.
His suggestion in the book is that
all wealthy countries, OECD,
should become plant-based meat,
all of them, and it would
save the environment.
He had a very great chapter about that.
Then I got an email from Starbucks.
They say, "Come in on Monday.
It's Meatless Monday."
Starbucks is not serving meat on Mondays,
and you can have lots of tasty
things, vegetarian things.
And I thought, "Oh my God.
When McDonald's and Starbucks
changed to vegetarian,
it means my karma is working.
It means this Lam Rim
bodhichitta meditation
is definitely working.
So I don't think it's superstitious.
I think it's real.
I want to encourage you to think
that we created that.
Those Lam Rim guys, and
those Medicine Buddha guys,
we changed McDonald's.
We made the meat industry vegetarian.
We made vegetarian meat. That's so cool.
I want to encourage you to believe in it.
Like don't be so skeptical
and don't be mean.
Don't say, "Ah, that's superstition."
It's not superstition.
I believe us Lam Rim guys,
and us Medicine Buddha guys,
we changed Starbucks, and
we changed McDonald's,
and we changed Bill
Gates with our Lam Rim.
So congratulations.
When you get to tantra, when
you get to the Diamond Way,
it's a bad deed not to believe
that you can change something.
It's a bad deed to think you
didn't change McDonald's.
So let's celebrate.
We changed McDonald's. Congratulations.
Do you know McDonald's
started in Phoenix, Arizona?
The first McDonald's
was next to the library.
My mom used to take us there.
She would buy us french fries.
That was about 50, 60
years ago. Unbelievable.
I never thought that I would
see a McDonald's hamburger
that's not hamburger.
Congratulations you guys.
Second advantage,
and ere we are reviewing the last Lam Rim.
So my idea for this
first class together is
we're just going to review the
then benefits of bodhichitta.
The first benefit is you
get this incredible karma
that can change anything.
We can say,
in Tibetan it's called
THEG CHEN GYI 'JUG SGO SEMS BSKYED
It's the only way to
get into the Mahayana.
So forget Mahayana as a
philosophy from ancient India.
Don't think like that.
Mahayana means jumping
from planet to planet.
And you got there. You are there.
Second one,
let's look at the Tibetan, Tim
RGYAL BA'I SRAS ZHES BYA BA'I MING THOB PA
RGYAL BA'I SRAS means
daughter or son of the Buddhas.
MING THOB PA means you get that name.
You get the name and
it's such a sexy name.
I think...There was a rock'n roll song
when I was younger called Bodhisattva.
I didn't know what's a
bodhisattva at that time
but it sounded so nice to me.
The word sounded so nice to me.
The song got very popular
and you will get the name Bodhisattva.
It's like, Tim, you're getting
a degree in the college.
They're giving you a degree.
It's like, Okay, that's
a Buddha on the left,
and you and me are on the right.
And Buddha's like, "Oh,
okay, this is your degree.
Now you have a new name like Dr. Tim."
Or I don't know, Pau Pachi Ph.D.
But now they're going to
call you Bodhisattva Tim
or Bodhisattva Pachi, Bodhisattva Gyelse.
And you got a new name.
And you get a new degree.
It's really, really beautiful.
It's so beautiful to know
that you're a bodhisattva.
When you hear people say bodhisattva,
I think bodhisattvas usually
don't tell people they're bodhisattvas.
But when you hear people say
bodhisattva, you're like,
"Yeah, that's me. They're
talking about me."
And you feel happy. You
just feel really happy.
"Oh yeah, I got that name.
I have that degree, Bodhisattva Degree."
That's the second benefit
Third benefit.
NYAN RANG RIGS KYI SGO NAS ZIL GYIS NON PA
This is very, very famous
and much, much described
in the commentaries.
NYAN RANG means listener,
NYAN means listener
and RANG means RANG SANGS
RGYAS self-made Buddha.
But the point is that
these are very, very deep
spiritual practitioners
who don't have that vision.
They don't have that vision of
going from planet to planet.
But they are very beautiful people
and their meditation is really great.
Their morality is perfect.
Their concentration is perfect.
Everything about them is really amazing.
And I like this picture of...
I had this idea of an ocean.
I saw this picture and it
reminded me of this idea
that the birds in the
picture are like arhats.
They reached nirvana.
These birds are to me, I like
to think they are listeners
and self-made buddhas.
It's beautiful to watch them
especially at sunset over
the ocean. But the sun.
But the sun.
You can see the reflection of the sun.
You cannot see the sun.
But compared to the sun,
the beauty of the birds is beautiful
but it's nothing compared to the sun.
The whole sun lighting up the whole world
compared to those birds.
The birds are beautiful. They are arhats.
They reached nirvana. They are listeners.
They are self-made buddhas.
They are people who
didn't have that vision,
bodhisattva vision.
And then sun is that higher vision.
And you become like the sun.
When you're a bodhisattva and
you have that higher vision,
you become like the sun.
It doesn't mean the
birds aren't beautiful.
They're beautiful.
In fact, the sun makes
them more beautiful.
But imagine if you could
be the birds and the sun,
something like that.
Fourth benefit is called
MCHOD PA'I ZHING MCHOG TU 'GYUR BA
MCHOD PA means to make offerings.
ZHING means garden, in this case, garden.
MCHOG TU 'GYUR BA means
you become the highest one.
You become the highest
garden where people can plant
a good karma of offering.
And I imagine, wouldn't it be cool
if you're really a
bodhisattva and you walk
into the coffee shop
and you order a coffee.
Like you just walk into the coffee...
we have a coffee shop next to the college.
I'm thinking of like, this
lady just became bodhisattva.
She had that vision.
Nobody knows she's a bodhisattva,
but she did reach that vision
in her meditation directly.
She saw the real thing.
And now this guy is offering
her a coffee and listen,
that guy offering her the coffee,
he suddenly makes this
intense, good karma.
He suddenly gets this
incredible good karma
because serving you a coffee
and you're bodhisattva.
So everyone who is sweet to a bodhisattva
is collecting extraordinary karma.
And wouldn't it be nice
to be the bodhisattva.
Every time someone comes close to you
and smiles at you or helps you in any way,
and they don't even know that their karma
is like a million times more,
they don't even know about it.
But you are making other people happy just
by drinking their coffee
at their coffee shop.
That's so cool.
Fifth benefit.
TSOGS RGYA CHEN PO BDE BLAG TU RDZOGS PA
TSOGS here means, some of
you heard the word TSOGS
for a dharma party and it means
a lots of good things to eat
and lots of good things to drink.
That's called a TSOGS.
Lots of cool offerings.
RGYA CHEN PO means very big,
and BDE BLAG TU RDZOGS PA
means you can make good karma
very, very quickly.
I was trying to think
of a photograph for this
and Gyelse, do you remember
when we first started
Diamond Mountain University,
the retreat center, then we
were thinking to build roads
so we could connect retreat cabins.
So, I don't know, a hundred
people went out in the desert
and we picked up rocks.
It was so funny.
A hundred people walked
about 50 steps in two hours
and we just pick up a rocks.
We'd throw them on the side
and we are making a road.
It was so funny and we worked so hard.
Oh my god, you guys go to
Diamond Mountain Retreat Center
now, you're so lucky.
People worked so hard.
And I remember we said,
"Let's build a road."
We used to do that in Boy Scouts.
Let's build a road.
We would work for like five days
and build a road for like a hundred yards.
So then we were all throwing rocks.
Then later we got more
money. We got more support.
And here's the picture.
Yeah. These machines
came to Diamond Mountain.
This is Diamond Mountain.
These are the machines that
were paid for by our sponsors.
And it's difficult. I took this picture.
The wheel of the machine
is bigger than me.
It's taller than me.
You can make a road, I
don't know, in a few hours.
You can push those big rocks
to the side, and bodhichitta,
this bodhisattva's heart, the
bodhisattva's mind is like
those big machines.
You want to make good karma?
It's good karma to pick up
rocks at Diamond Mountain
but it's going to take you a
hundred years to build a road.
Go get one of those stupid machines.
The tire is bigger than
me, taller than me,
and just use it for a couple
of hours and finish the roads.
The karma of being a
bodhisattva is like that,
very, very powerful and very efficient.
Benefit number six.
SDIG SGRIB MYUR DU SBYANG BA
That means,
SDIG SGRIB means obstacles.
So we all did bad things in our life.
We still remember. We're still doing them.
We can't stop ourselves.
Sometimes we do bad things.
We hurt people. We do things
we're not supposed to do.
And then immediately it creates
an obstacle in our life.
We've been doing that for our whole life,
many years collecting
obstacles, one by one.
We can remove them just by
having that bodhisattva vision.
So let's call bodhichitta:
the vision of a bodhisattva,
just by imagining going
from planet to planet, helping people.
Just thinking about it
can remove all these obstacles you have
in your business life, in your health,
in your relationships,
in your state of mind.
Just imagining once in a while
this goal of dancing from planet
to planet is enough to
remove all those obstacles.
You can take medicines.
You can go to doctors.
You can go to marriage counselors.
You can talk to business
consultants for many years
and you won't remove the
obstacles like you can
with a few short bodhichitta meditations.
It's just very cool. It's very efficient.
Saves a lot of money also.
Benefit number seven.
CI BSAM PA GRUB PA
CI BSAM PA means whatever you want,
anything you can think of.
CI BSAM PA is a nice word.
It means anything you can think of.
GRUB PA You can get it,
anything you can think of.
I love this organic way to
get things in your life.
I don't worry about money
and it was never my goal
in my life to be wealthy.
I thought if I tried I could
be, but it's not my priority.
It's not something I want.
But I would like to have a
lot of money. It would be fun.
I could do so many good things.
Mr. Binh in Vietnam,
he just built 400 houses for poor people.
I think that's so cool.
I would like to have money like that.
And I would like to have
a perfect relationship
at home with my wife.
I'd like that to be, and
I'd like to be healthy.
I don't want to be sick.
Those are things I want.
And the amazing thing is,
just this bodhisattva vision,
just thinking about it once in a while,
things start to happen in your life.
The karma is so intense that
cool stuff starts to happen
in your life and you start
to build this perfect world
without thinking about it.
You're not like, "Oh, I want to get rich."
Or you're not like, "Oh, I
want to be super healthy."
But suddenly all these
things are happening to you.
If you keep coming back to this vision,
you got a picture for me,
Pachi, City in the Sun.
I'm thinking this is a
picture of like Shenzhen.
In a way, this is a beautiful combination.
I love this city in China
because they mix these
beautiful buildings with nature.
And as you walked through the city,
there's a beautiful balance.
People need homes to stay
and people need offices.
So there are these beautiful buildings
and there's a sensitivity
to the environment.
And there's a nice mixture
in that particular city of nature.
And without thinking, without planning,
if you just come back to this
vision a few times a day,
the karma is so intense that
you will start to have beauty
and physical wealth around
you, that you didn't dream of,
and beautiful relationships
and things you didn't dream of.
Number eight
Benefit number eight
GNOD PA DANG BAR CHAD KYIS MI TSUGS PA
GNOD PA means things that
would cause you trouble.
BAR CHAD means interruption.
My teacher used to get really
irritated if he was meditating
and someone would knock
on the door or something.
That's called BAR CHAD
BAR CHAD means your
meditation's going really good
and then somebody knocks on the door.
That's called BAR CHAD
So if you have this vision,
a bodhisattva's vision,
then those BAR CHADs,
okay, you'll be protected.
I liked the picture--
Pachi, are you ready? --
of a tank.
And look, I know it's a military thing.
I know it's not a nice thing. It's true.
It's a very bad thing.
When tanks...still in this world,
country's power is calculated
by the number of tanks.
Still, they say this
country has four thousand.
This country has three thousand.
This country has a hundred thousand tanks.
And if you can imagine a war,
and if you imagine bullets
flying here and there,
and people getting killed,
every few yards, every few
meters somebody's dying,
then there's this guy
relaxing in the tank,
probably he's having
a cappuccino, I guess.
And there's bullets and bombs,
and people dying, and he just relaxing
in the tank because nothing
can get through the tank.
And I know in the
movies, they like to show
Brad Pitt goes out and
hits the tank with his hand
and it breaks down.
It's not like that in a real war.
The tank comes through
and kills everybody.
The guys in the tank are just relaxing
and you can't touch them.
So bodhichitta is like sitting in a tank.
The whole world can be crazy and insane,
people can be doing terrible
things to each other,
and you're just in this bubble
of bodhichitta protection.
Just things don't happen to you
like they happen to other
people: disasters, problems,
all kinds of disturbances
in their life happened.
And even you feel guilty, "Oh
I am in the bodhichitta bubble
and other people are not
and look they're having so much trouble."
Yesterday, a friend of mine,
her brother committed suicide.
And I have to see this.
I have to meet her.
I have to talk to her.
I feel like, "Oh, just get in the bubble.
Just get in the tank.
Just think about
bodhichitta once in a while,
you will have this.
You can be protected."
That's the eighth benefit.
Ninth benefit.
SA LAM THAMS CAD MYUR DU RDZOGS PA
SA LAM
SA means bodhisattva levels and
LAM means path.
THAMS CAD MYUR DU RDZOGS PA means quickly,
you'll go through all those paths.
So the spiritual progress
is judged by five paths
and ten bodhisattva levels.
It's very hard to get to the first one.
It's very hard to get to
the first bodhisattva level.
When you get to the
first bodhisattva level,
you already saw emptiness directly.
That's number one. Imagine
what is number ten.
But if you have bodhichitta,
it's like you're climbing a mountain
and you're just at the top,
right away you're at the
top. No trouble. No work.
You don't feel tired.
Just suddenly
that bodhichitta can take you to the top,
Without much trouble, without much sweat,
without much hard work.
If you just practice that vision
we talked about the beginning,
then it's automatic.
You go to the top of the
ten bodhisattva levels.
Last benefit.
'GRO BA'I BDE SKYID MA LUS PA BYUNG BA'I
ZHING SAR 'GYUR BA'O
'GRO BA'I BDE SKYID
BDE SKYID
I have a friend here in Sedona.
Her name is, they call her Dickie,
but her real name is BDE SKYID
BDE SKYID here it is.
BDE SKYID means super happy. Super happy.
I'll show a picture.
This is valley
and this whole valley I imagined
there was a river going through there.
The whole valley is covered
with nice, beautiful soil,
fertile soil.
You put seeds there, it grows.
There's places like that.
Not Arizona.
But there are places
where the soil is so good
that just everything will
grow there automatically,
without any work at all.
Things will grow there.
And oftentimes, it's river soil.
The tenth benefit of the
vision of the bodhisattva
is that you become like a valley
of fertile soil for other people.
You become like,
people can plant their crops in you.
What crops? Their happiness.
You are like the good soil.
And just by being around other people,
they're good karma increases
and they can plant their
happiness in you, with you.
You're available. You're nearby
and you give them a chance.
Somebody says good morning to bodhisattva
but they're like already
going to be in nirvana
within ten years.
It's crazy.
So it's nice to be the
soil that other people
can use to grow their crops
that they need to live
and to be happy.
It's nice to be the person in the room
that is a very fertile soil
for the happiness of other people.
And needless to say,
when you become a Buddha,
after you go through bodhichitta,
with bodhichitta motivation,
you become a Buddha.
Then obviously, it's just
cool to be the person
who makes billions of other people happy.
In the end, we are not selfish.
Human beings are not selfish.
We want to make other people happy.
It makes us happy when we
make other people happy.
And we know that. We feel that.
And a bodhisattva is going to be the one
who makes everybody else happy.
Just imagine you're able to throw a party
for the whole billions of people
because you have this bodhichitta.
So that's a review of the last
Lam Rim course that we had.
That was just a short review
of what we went through in
the last Lam Rim course.
Now we're going to start
the actual instructions
for how to get to this vision.
There's actually seven steps,
easy steps, we can take.
And that's going to be
the new Lam Rim course
that we're starting on now.
Let's learn the seven steps we can all do
to get to this vision.
So I'll see you in the next episode. Yay!